in this tutorial we're going to take a deeper
dive into macros in the last episode we built
some predefined macros on the GrandMA 3 in this
tutorial we're going to go deeper and we're going
to start writing our own macros i'm going to
show you where you find your inspiration to what
to write if you haven't been working with macros
at any time so what we're going to build is this
we have all our vipers up here if i turn
them on you can see it's only one cue
and it it's just all the vipers on in a certain
position but if i push this button here you can
see it creates two or sorry three extra cues here
with three different effects on it so if i push
my go button now you can see effect number one
effect number two and effect number three and
then it goes back to the first cue i can select
another sequence up here i can turn them on that's
all our auras turn the vipers off i can push
the button and it does the exact same thing
one effect two effect three effect and
nothing so this is what we're gonna build so
hang tight and welcome to the channel if you
haven't been here before the first thing we need
to do we select all our vipers again and we open
a new macro here and we go into the command line
or the edit we need to create a new command
line but we have no idea what to write if
we haven't worked with macros before so
here's a few tips on how to how to do that
so let's just close this one down again and say
okay what do we want to do we need to take all
our moving lights all our vipers and put them into
this position this is going to start a an effect
and this is what we want to do we just want to
do it on a macro so let's clear this one out and
say okay we close all them all the auras down
take all the vipers up again and say all right
we push all our vipers and how
can we make a macro that does that
we go into our m a down here and
it's gonna tell you what it did
all the last commands so the last command was cell
fix group number one but we don't want a selfix
group number one because group number one is all
our vipers so basically we just needed to selfix
or select all our fixtures in a sequence
GrandMA 3 is so cool that if you have
a sequence selected you can simply put selfix down
here and if we just turn off our shortcuts and say
selfix select all fixtures it selects
everything that's inside the selected
sequence so this is what we need to write
in our macro so let's just clear out here go
into our macro go into edit and say insert
new macro line right click and say
selfix there we go let's just go out here and see
if it worked so we run our macro and it selected
everything that's in this sequence which is all
our vipers so now what do we need the vipers to do
we need to go into this effect down here which is
in our all preset and if you can see the number 21
here and if you can see the number two here on our
position 3 on gobo 6 on focus if we press this one
and we go into our ma thing down here again you
can say it's selfix it and it went to add
preset 21.1 and 21.1 is 21 as the preset pool if
you weigh and then number one is the first effect
so basically we clear out here and we go into
our macro again and we say we just selfix
all our moving lights if we insert a new
command line here and we say at preset
21.1 and let's see what the console is doing
now so we clear out and we say run the macro
you can see it selected the vipers and it
put it into 21.1 which is our dimmer sinus
so basically now we have everything
in our macro to activate the
effect so now we need to store it and and that
is really really easy because you basically
just write out what you needed to do so insert a
new line go into it and say okay we store cue 2
and we need to add a dash and an o which means
that it overrides the cue if there's a cue
there already right now there's no cue
so it's going to work without the o but if
the if the cue already exists it's actually
going to stop and ask you what you need to do
if you want a merge if you want to insert or
if you want to override or whatever so that's
why we put the dash and the o in and you can also
say dash m which is merge and that's i i think
for insert and all the other you can say remove as
well so basically this is gonna store cue number
two and override whatever is in it in the first
place so let's see if it works we run the macro
there we go and it actually now has the dimmer
sinus as i can see i activated the macro when
i built this tutorial so let's just delete
cue 2 through 4 that's another macro i have
there we go so we clear it again and
we run the macro and it built the
cue number 2 as we wanted to and there we
go so now we go into the macro again and say okay
it start cue number 2 but
it's called it dimmer sinus
we wanna we wanna decide what what to call it so
let's say insert new macro line let's say label
cue 2 and then we put these quotation marks in
and say sinus effect like this and let's go
back and see if it worked so we run it again
and let's see if the name changes up here
and it did so now it's basically
copy paste what i need to do is
my all preset here i want to use effect number one
number two and number four in basically cue two
three and four so let's say we go into the macro
again and say we stored cue number two we put the
the preset number 21.1 on the effect we stored
it in cue number two and we did some override
we labeled cue 2 sinus effect so basically what we
need to do now is we still have the selection
we made up here so it's very simple now
to copy whatever is in here just ctrl c
and then paste it here and say now we need it
at preset 21.2 and we need to store that in cue
we just i just copy it so we don't have to
write it out all the time we store this in cue 3
we label cue 3 copy and paste it here we say snap on
snap on effect so let's see if that
worked let's run the macro again
it now did it again here there we go maybe we did
something with the cue that is not right that's
because i should change this to a 3 and that's
the cool thing about macros because then i can
just run it again and everything is correct
so let's build out the last one we go into
the macro again and we say we need it at preset
we just copy this one and go down here and say
here we go at number 21.4 we need to store this in
we need to store this in cue number 4 so we
need to change this to a 4 and we need to label
we need to label cue 4
there we go and we can call
it just wing effect maybe
wing effect there we go so now let's go out again
and see if it worked so we just clear everything
and we run the macro and everything worked
fine so a good thing to do when you have done
all this macro and you can you can see it's
working now we need to put the console into
blind mode before we continue before we start the
macro and that is done by inserting a new macro
line and simply typing blind there we go and we
can insert the last one where we take blind off
i think it's only blind again i'm not sure
maybe it's going to work let's just try it out
right now the disk is not in blind if we run
the macro everything is fine and it's not in
blind so it takes it into blind and then goes
out but we need to add the clear command as well
so and we need to do that
before the blind is turned
off which is we just put it here and
insert new macro line and we say clear
all and for some reason you have to
do that twice uh i don't really get
it because there was another command on it
uh on the GrandMA 2 but i don't know why
this should work so let's just take this one
out we just clear everything here and run
the macro like this and it just stays where
it is and right now you can use the effects
and it's really cool but if we select
all our auras we need all ours to have
the cue 2 - 3 and 4 as well and labeled in the same way
so basically we select it and say okay all our auras
we turn them on we turn the vipers off there's
only one cue here but if we run our macro now
it populated cue number 2 - 3 and 4
i can press go i have all the effects i want
and that took only a second so basically
this macro is really cool if you need to do the
same thing over and over again to apply effects
or colors or whatever i mean this is only for
inspiration you can write very very complex macros
change timing and do whatever so this is just for
inspiring you and if you enjoyed this video please like the video and maybe even subscribe to the
channel that is going to help us against the evil
youtube algorithm and spread the video out to
more people so thank you for watching and i
hope to see you next time on the channel bye bye